<chapter id="authority">
  <title>Being an Authority</title>

  <para>
    As an authority, you are tasked with sharing the responsibility of
    maintaining the security of an election.  As daunting as that
    sounds, this job fortunately requires little work on your part.
  </para>

  <para>
    If you would like a greater understanding of the reasons behind
    why Adder uses a multi-authority system, refer to <xref
    linkend="concepts" />.
  </para>

  <section id="authority-before">
    <title>Before You Begin</title>

    <para>
      Before you can begin functioning as an authority, you must have
      the proper information from your election administrator,
      including a username, password, hostname, and an SSL certficate.
      Assuming you have this information, following the instructions
      in <xref linkend="addergui-ssl" /> to install the SSL certficate
      and in <xref linkend="addergui-connecting" /> to connect to the
      server.  Next, you must select a key directory as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-screen-auth-keydirs" />. This must be a directory
      that you have write access to. The default filenames should be
      fine.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-screen-auth-keydirs">
      <title>The Key Locations Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/screen-auth-keydirs.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="authority-participating">
    <title>Participating</title>
    <para>
      As an authority, you are required to participate in several
      stages of an election.  Once you connect to the server, you
      should be able to perform these tasks by selecting the
      <guibutton>Participate</guibutton> option, logging in, and
      following the instructions.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="authority-security">
    <title>Security Checklist</title>
    <para>
      Please ensure that you have taken as the following security measures.
    </para>
    
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Protecting key files from being read by anyone else.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Protecting key files from being accidentally deleted.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Ensuring that your passwords is kept secret
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Verifying that you install the correct SSL certificate as
          given to you by the election administrator.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Notifying the administrator of <emphasis>and</emphasis>
          suspicions you notice.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>