<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="introduction-what">
    <title>What is Adder?</title>

    <para>
      <application>Adder</application> is a <emphasis>free</emphasis>
      and <emphasis>open-source</emphasis> electronic voting system.
      employing strong cryptography. Our system is a fully functional
      e-voting platform and enjoys a number of security properties,
      such as robustness, trust distribution, ballot privacy,
      auditability and verifiability. It can readily implement and
      carry out various voting procedures in parallel and can be used
      for small scale boardroom/department-wide voting as well as
      large-scale elections. In addition,
      <application>Adder</application> employs a flexible voting
      scheme which allows the system to carry out procedures such as
      surveys or other data collection
      activities. <application>Adder</application> offers a unique
      opportunity to study cryptographic voting protocols from a
      systems perspective and to explore the security and usability of
      electronic voting systems.
    </para>

    <para>
      By "free," we mean that you are free to do with
      <application>Adder</application> as you please.  You can run it in
      your organization, study the source code, make changes, share it
      with your friends, sell it, or anything else you like.  We feel
      that reliable electronic voting is something that everyone should
      have access to, which is why we created this system.
    </para>

    <para>
      By "open-source," we mean that the source code to
      <application>Adder</application> is out in the open.  We believe
      that this is the only realistic way to create an electronic voting
      system.  Commercial vendors of electronic voting systems often
      hide their source code, possibly to avoid revealing embarassing
      security flaws.  With <application>Adder</application>, you can be
      assured that the software blueprints are visible at all times.  If
      you would like to use <application>Adder</application> to conduct
      an election, you can perform your own audit of the code to ensure
      its security and correctness.  If you are not yourself a
      programmer, you can hire someone to inspect the code for you.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="introduction-goals">
    <title>Goals</title>
    <para>
      We hope that <application>Adder</application> will be used for
      many types of elections, not just large-scale political ones.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Small political elections</emphasis>.  If there is little risk of a
          large-scale attack on the system, then <application>Adder</application> would be
          well-suited.  For example, <application>Adder</application> would be well-suited for
          town government elections.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Student government elections</emphasis>.  <application>Adder</application>'s easy-to-use voting
          applet is ideal for students to run over the Web.  <application>Adder</application> can
          help students at universities and colleges become more
          involved in their schools.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Organizational elections</emphasis>. In small
          organizations, where voting members are likely to know each
          other, election privacy may be important.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Experimenting with cryptography</emphasis>.
          <application>Adder</application>'s cryptographic library is
          well-documented, and we hope that people who are interested
          in cryptography will explore it.
          <application>Adder</application> provides an interesting
          opportunity as a cryptographic system that is designed to be
          used by non-technical users.  It will hopefully provide good
          insight into how ordinary users understand security and
          cryptography.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      From a technological perspective, <application>Adder</application>
      strives toward the following goals.
    </para>
    
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Transparency</emphasis>. All of the data in the main
          server database should be accessible to the public. This
          includes the encrypted votes, public encryption keys, and
          final totals. The main server database does not store secrets.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Universal Verifiability</emphasis>. Any result
          obtained by the system should be verifiable by any third
          party. By inspecting the election transcript, it should be
          possible to perform a complete audit of any procedure.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Privacy</emphasis>. All voters in an election
          should be confident that their individual choices will
          remain hidden. Only the total is made available to the
          public.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Distributed Trust</emphasis>. Each procedure is
          "supervised" by multiple authorities, and the final sum
          cannot be revealed without the cooperation of a given number
          of authorities. Any attempt to undermine the procedure will
          require the corruption of a set number of
          authorities. Authorities and voters may overlap
          arbitrarily. Thus, it is possible for the voters themselves
          to ensure trustworthiness.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="introduction-installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>
      <application>Adder</application> consists of the following components.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          libadder - the cryptographic library
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          cryptoserver - the main server
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          php-adder - a set of php scripts to allow voting over the Web
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          mozilla-plugin-adder/<application>Adder</application>Ctrl/libadder-java - respectively,
          Mozilla plugin, IE control, and Java applet to be used with
          php-adder (all henceforth refered to as "browser plugins.")
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <application>Adder</application>GUI - a Qt-based GUI and verification suite for administration
          and advanced election functionality.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      If you would like to administer your own election server, you will
      want to install libadder, cryptoserver, and php-adder on the server,
      and <application>Adder</application>GUI and/or a browser plugin on each of the clients.
      If you would like to participate in <application>Adder</application> elections that are already
      running, you will only need to install either a browser plugin or
      <application>Adder</application>GUI.
    </para>
    
    <section id="introduction-installation-libadder">
      <title>Cryptographic Library</title>

      <para>The dependencies of libadder are:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>GMP, version 4.1.3 or greater</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>OpenSSL</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Doxygen API documentation can be built by running 'doxygen' in the
      'src' directory.</para>
    </section>

    
    <section id="introduction-installation-addergui">
    <title><application>Adder</application>GUI</title>
    <para>
      The system requirements of <application>Adder</application>GUI are:
    </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>libadder</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Qt 4</para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
          <para>QConf</para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
          <para>Boost.Regex</para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
          <para>QCA2</para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
          <para>QCA2-OpenSSL
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Type the following commands to build and install <application>Adder</application>GUI:</para>
      
      <screen>
$ qconf
$ ./configure --prefix=&lt;prefix&gt; --bindir=&lt;bindir&gt; --qtdir=&lt;qtdir&gt;
$ make
$ make INSTALL_ROOT=&lt;INSTALL_ROOT&gt; install
      </screen>
      
      <important>
        <para>
          There seems to be a problem with <application>GCC
          4.1</application>.  It takes forever to compile
          <filename>Client.cpp</filename>.  Stick with
          <application>GCC 4.0</application> for now.
        </para>
      </important>
</section>

  <section id="introduction-installation-cryptoserver">
    <title>CryptoServer</title>
    
    <para>To install an <application>Adder</application> server, you
    must install the following components.</para>
    
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>libadder</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>cryptoserver</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>php-adder</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>
      This section explains how to configure the cryptoserver.  For
      help with libadder and php-adder, you should read the sections
      on those two components.
    </para>

    <para>The dependencies of cryptoserver are:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>libadder</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>ACE, version 5.4.2 or greater</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>MySQL++, version 1.7.19</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>MySQL, version 4.0.21 or greater</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>OpenSSL, version 0.9.7d or greater</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Once all of the dependencies are installed, you can compile and
    install cryptoserver as follows.</para>

    <screen>
$ ./configure
$ make
$ make install
    </screen>

    <para>Next, you must configure the MySQL database.  Change into the
    'database' directory, and enter the following commands.
    </para>

    <screen>
# mysqladmin create adder
# mysql adder &lt; schema.sql
# mysql adder &lt; permissions.sql
    </screen>

    <para>
      You should now configure the
      <filename>/etc/cryptoserver.conf</filename> file to your liking.
    </para>

    <warning>
      <para>
        In our experience running Ubuntu on linux/ppc, MySQL++ does
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> work with the cryptoserver.  It will
        crash frequently.
      </para>
    </warning>
  </section>

  <section id="introduction-installation-web">
    <title>Web Interface</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
</chapter>